Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. I guess travel around in.
All right. All right. Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So we
pick up today, today's daf דף daf is daled ד, daled, where
we're a little behind. We pick up on gimmel amud bet ג
עמוד ב. gimmel amud bet. But at least we start now getting
to—we're done with all the linguistic analysis of the mishna משנה, mishna,
and we start turning our attention to, what do you call it,
to the actual basis for all of this. Let's take a look.
The Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this: Mana hani milei? מנא הני
מילי Mana hani milei?
Detanu rabanan דתנו רבנן. Detanu rabanan. So we're about eight lines from
the top on gimmel amud bet ג עמוד ב. gimmel amud bet.
Where does this come from? This whole idea that there's an idea
that a tzara
צרה—first tzara of all, that there's no mitzvah מצוה mitzvah of yibbum
יבום yibbum in the case of an ervah ערוה, ervah, that one
of the women that the woman is an ervah ערוה ervah to
the man who would do yibbum יבום, yibbum, other than being to
his husband, his brother's wife. And that there's an exemption for the
tzara צרה tzara for the co-wives. Detanu rabanan דתנו רבנן, Detanu rabanan,
as our Rabbis taught: Isha el achota lo tikach אשה אל אחתה
לא תקח. Isha el achota lo tikach. Do not take a woman,
a woman and her sister, litzror לצרור, litzror, to sort of agitate,
to rub against one another, you know, so sort of like to
for the friction, you know, create friction, legalot ervata aleha bechayeha לגלות
ערותה עליה בחייה, legalot ervata aleha bechayeha, to reveal her nakedness on
her, in her life. Meaning, so in the life of the of
the wife, of the first wife. So that by the way, the
issue came up before about how many whether these arayot עריות arayot
apply after they, you know, the relationship has has changed and, you
know, there's been a divorce or a death or whatever. Anyway, so
the general assumption is yes, but here the verse says bechayeha בחייה.
bechayeha. So the problem of a woman and her sister is only
while while the original wife is still alive. Okay, so that's the
prohibition. Now, ma talmud lomar? מה תלמוד לומר ma talmud lomar? What
does it teach us? Lefi shene'emar לפי שנאמר, Lefi shene'emar, since the
verse says yevama yavo aleha יבמה יבוא עליה, yevama yavo aleha, that
the brother-in-law shall come onto her with, meaning have sex with her,
with the with the wife of his dead brother, shomeia ani afilu
be'achat mikol ha'arayot shebamishnah peturah שומע אני אפילו באחת מכל העריות שבמשנה
פטורה, shomeia ani afilu be'achat mikol ha'arayot shebamishnah peturah, maybe it would
even override the prohibition of arayot עריות. arayot. And normally that would
be strange, how you would think it would override the prohibition of
arayot עריות. arayot. It's a mitzvah מצוה, mitzvah, but arayot עריות arayot
is an issur kareit איסור כרת, issur kareit, and a mitzvat asei
מצות עשה mitzvat asei doesn't normally override. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara
will look at that. Maybe I would have thought it would, but
particularly if it overrides the prohibition of brother's wife, maybe it would
override other arayot עריות arayot as well. That certainly one way to
understand the hava amina הוה אמינא. hava amina. So ne'emar kan נאמר
כאן, ne'emar kan, hakasuv m'daber הכתוב מדבר, hakasuv m'daber, maybe even in
that case. So ne'emar kan aleha נאמר כאן עליה. ne'emar kan aleha.
It says here yevama yavo aleha יבמה יבוא עליה. yevama yavo aleha.
Vene'emar lehalan aleha ונאמר להלן עליה, vene'emar lehalan aleha, and it says
not take a isha el achota lo tikach litzror legalot ervata aleha
אשה אל אחתה לא תקח לצרור לגלות ערותה עליה isha el achota
lo tikach litzror legalot ervata aleha by a wife's sister. So ma
lehalan bemakom mitzvah מה להלן במקום מצוה, ma lehalan bemakom mitzvah, so
the same way, actually I think the ne'emar kan נאמר כאן ne'emar
kan is the wife's sister and lehalan להלן lehalan by the yevama
יבמה yevama case. Anyway, ma lehalan bemakom mitzvah מה להלן במקום מצוה,
ma lehalan bemakom mitzvah, the same way later the mitzvah מצוה mitzvah
of yibbum יבום, yibbum, the aleha עליה aleha means when there's a
mitzvah מצוה mitzvah of yibbum יבום. yibbum. That's the case. So af
kan אף כאן, af kan, even here when it says don't marry
a woman and her sister, bemakom mitzvah במקום מצוה, bemakom mitzvah, it
means even when there's a mitzvah מצוה mitzvah of yibbum יבום. yibbum.
So the word aleha עליה aleha is being used to mean even
in mean a case of yibbum יבום. yibbum. Since it says yevama
yavo aleha יבמה יבוא עליה, yevama yavo aleha, the word aleha עליה
aleha means in a case of yibbum יבום. yibbum. So now we
read the prohibition of a wife and her sister, and it says
isha el achota lo tikach אשה אל אחתה לא תקח, isha el
achota lo tikach, do not marry a woman and her sister, litzror
legalot ervata aleha לצרור לגלות ערותה עליה, litzror legalot ervata aleha, aleha
עליה. aleha. Don't marry a woman and her sister even in a
case of aleha עליה, aleha, even in a case of yibbum יבום.
yibbum. So do you understand how because aleha עליה aleha by yibbum
יבום yibbum is about yibbum יבום, yibbum, so the aleha עליה aleha
by not marrying a wife and her sister means even in a
case of yibbum יבום? yibbum? Even when the husband of one of
them died. Right. Even when there's a mitzvah מצוה mitzvah of yibbum
יבום yibbum it does not override the prohibition of a wife and
her sister.
So okay, ve'amar rachmana ואמר רחמנא ve'amar rachmana lo tikach לא תקח,
lo tikach, and it says even in that case you cannot marry
even though it's a case of yibbum יבום. yibbum. Ve'ein li ela
hi ואין לי אלא היא. ve'ein li ela hi. Now I know
that there's no mitzvah מצוה mitzvah of yibbum יבום yibbum by a
wife's by by a wife's sister. Tzaratah minayin צרתה מנין? tzaratah minayin?
How do you know it also doesn't you're also no mitzvah מצוה
mitzvah of yibbum יבום yibbum by the co-wife of the wife's sister?
Talmud lomar litzror תלמוד לומר לצרור Talmud lomar litzror because the word
of litzror לצרור litzror to agitate, to create friction, is understood to
be a tzara צרה, tzara, a co-wife, right, like we have that
by Chanah and Peninah חנה ופנינה, Chanah and Peninah, right? Ve'ki'asata tzaratah
gam ka'as וכעסתה צרתה גם כעס. ve'ki'asata tzaratah gam ka'as. What? It's
not in the Torah, it's a drasha דרשה. drasha. Okay, but litzror
לצרור litzror now represents that the mitzvah מצוה mitzvah of yibbum יבום
yibbum doesn't apply for her and litzror לצרור litzror for the tzararah
צררה. tzararah. Ve'ein li ela tzaratah ואין לי אלא צרתה, ve'ein li
ela tzaratah, I only know the the wife's sister and her tzara
צרה, tzara, her co-wife. Tzarat tzaratah minayin צרת צרתה מנין? tzarat tzaratah
minayin? How do I know that it then is the co-wife of
the co-wife? That if then this co-wife goes and marries another brother
and he dies, that the that not only is she exempt but
her co-wife is also exempt? Talmud lomar litzror תלמוד לומר לצרור Talmud
lomar litzror velo litzor ולא לצרור, velo litzor, the double resh. It
doesn't say לצור, latsor, it says לצרור, litsror, which means even the
צרה tsarah of a צרה, tsarah, right? So since it's reading the
word צרה, tsarah, לצור latsor could have been that, לצרור litsror means
a צרה tsarah of a צרה. tsarah. So that's how we get
it. Now there is a question why you need a separate פסוק,
pasuk, right, why it doesn't just become, right, the issue, because everybody
understands that what happens is, here you've got, well, here you have
רחל Rachel and לאה, Leah, okay? And here's ראובן Reuven is married
to רחל Rachel and שמעון Shimon is married to לאה Leah and
he's married to לאה Leah and to, I don't know, חנה, Chana,
okay? So then he goes ahead and he dies. So חנה Chana
is the צרה, tsarah, right? This is his wife's sister לאה, Leah,
right? חנה Chana is the צרה. tsarah. She goes and she marries
לוי, Levi, okay? And now לוי Levi is married to חנה Chana
and to, who?
פנינה. Penina. So לוי Levi dies. So then not only is חנה
Chana exempt from ראובן Reuven because that's the צרה, tsarah, but פנינה
Penina is also exempt, because that's the צרת צרה. tsarat tsarah. Now
the question is, the גמרא Gemara learns it from a פסוק, pasuk,
it's a weak, you know, or whatever, it's based on לצרור לצור,
litsror latsor, whatever, hard to understand how you get all of that
out of it. But there is an interesting question which we're going
to be returning to which is, do you really need another פסוק?
pasuk? Once there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum in this case,
then what's חנה's Chana status to ראובן Reuven if there's no מצוה
mitzvah of יבום? yibum? She's אשת אח. eshet ach. She's an ערוה.
ervah. She's, she's, she's an ערוה. ervah. Okay, if there's no מצוה
mitzvah of יבום, yibum, then she's an ערוה, ervah, right? So then
she marries לוי, Levi, so even though here there would be a
מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, maybe חנה Chana remains forbidden to her
from just the status of אשת אח, eshet ach, that original status
from being an ערוה ervah maybe, maybe of, maybe obtained. So is
this really a צרת צרה, tsarat tsarah, or just, right, or is
it really that's how the גמרא's Gemara conceiving it, because it started
as a צרה, tsarah, or could you say once she becomes a
צרה tsarah she also becomes an ערוה ervah of אשת אח, eshet
ach, right?
Are you both sort of with me? Once there's no מצוה mitzvah
of יבום, yibum, then the woman becomes a הלכה halachic status of
an ערוה ervah of an אשת אח. eshet ach. So anyway, so
that's an interesting question whether you really need a פסוק pasuk which
would exempt פנינה Penina
and then פנינה Penina becomes אשת אח, eshet ach, so that the
whole idea of צרה tsarah and צרת צרה tsarat tsarah could be
understood as just generating more cases of אשת אח eshet ach than
there than there's always,
so anyway, yeah. So it's an interesting question whether conceptually there really
is a separate category of צרת צרה tsarat tsarah or really just
creates a reality of אשת אח, eshet ach, okay? But anyway, the
גמרא Gemara gets that from the case of not לצור latsor but
לצרור. litsror. Okay, ואין לי אלא ve’ein li ella back to the
גמרא, Gemara, ואין לי אלא אחות אשה. ve'ein li ella achot ishah.
Now I know that this idea that the an ערוה ervah is
exempt and her צרה tsarah is exempt applies by wife's sister. שאר
עריות מנין? She'ar arayot minayin? How do I know that there's an
exemption from יבום yibum for the other עריות? arayot? So אמרה מה
אחות אשה מיוחדת שהיא ערוה וחייבין על זדונה כרת ועל שגגתה חטאת,
Amrah mah achot ishah miyuchedet shehi ervah vechayavin al zedonah koret veal
shigegatah chatat, it's basically just use it as a paradigm. So wife's
sister is an עריות, arayos, there's a כרת koret if it's transgressed
intentionally, a חטאת chatat if it's unintentionally, ואסורה ליבם. ve’asurah leyavam. So
what's the status of somebody that's an ערוה ervah as an איסור
כרת? issur koret? Is that there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum,
she's forbidden to the יבם. yavam. אף כל שהיא ערוה וחייבין על
זדונה כרת ועל שגגתה חטאת, Af kol shehi ervah vechayavin al zedonah
koret veal shigegatah chatat, anybody who is a similarly an ערוה ervah
and his, the punishment is כרת koret or worse,
ואסורה ליבם ve’asurah leyavam should equally be forbidden to the brother-in-law. So
basically it's a מה מצינו, mah matzinu, it's a paradigm. Look, there's
nothing that should make this case, you know, unique, so we'll assume
if it's true by a wife's sister it should be true by
all the עריות. arayos. Now that's in terms of ואין לי אלא
הן. ve’ein li ella hen. Now that's in terms of being able
to infer that other עריות arayos there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום,
yibum, that's step number one. צרותיהן מנין? Tsaroteihen minayin? Where do I
would know that by other עריות arayos their co-wives would also be
exempt? So אמר, amar, similar type of a paradigm, מה ידעת, mah
yadata, מה מצינו, mah matzinu, of like a just like infer from
a particular case to a general rule. So מנין אמרת? Minayin amarta?
מה אחות אשה מיוחדת שהיא ערוה וחייבין על זדונה כרת ועל שגגתה
חטאת ואסורה ליבם וצרתה אסורה. Mah achot ishah miyuchedet shehi ervah vechayavin
al zedonah koret veal shigegatah chatat ve'asurah leyavam vetsaratah asurah. אחותיך, Achotecha,
thank you. So, okay, found a solution.
So the same story. Here's this woman, the wife's sister is an
ערוה ervah that you're חייב כרת. chayav koret. So what's the הלכה
halachah of that? Not only is she exempt and אסור, assur, but
her צרה tsarah is exempt and an אסור. assur. So we'll make
the same type of rule for other people that fall into a
similar case.
Where would be the situation where there would be another?
What do you mean, any of the other עריות? arayos? Daughter, granddaughter,
mother, grandmother, you know, whatever, all the other 15 עריות arayos in
our משנה.
mishnah. This is מיוחדת, miyuchedet, it's really not מיוחדת miyuchedet at all.
What? Yeah, what's distinctive, not unique, distinctive. Okay, so the relevant distinctive
characteristics here is that she's an ערוה, ervah, okay, and a serious
ערוה. ervah. You're חייב כרת. chayav kareis. And what's the הלכה? halacha?
No מצות mitzvas of יבום yibum and the צרה tzara is exempt.
So we'll say that by all עריות. arayos. So,
וצרתה אסורה אף כל שכן ערווה וחייב על זדונה כרת ועל שגגתה
חטאת, v'tzarasah asurah af kol shekain ervah v'chayav al zdonah kareis v'al
shigagatah chatas, anybody who's an עריות arayos and it's a serious one,
it's a חייב כרת, chayav kareis, ואסורה ליבם, v'asurah l'yavam, and once
we've established stage number one that because she's in that category she's
forbidden to the brother-in-law, so therefore the second stage will apply: צרתה
אסורה, tzarasah asurah, the co-wife would be forbidden. So that's where you
get the general principle of העריות פטורות ופוטרות צרותיהן. ha'arayos pturot v'poterot
tzoroseihen. עריות arayos is exempt, co-wife is exempt. We learn it from
אחות אישה achot isha and then we generalize to all the עריות.
arayos. מכאן אמרו חכמים, mikan amru chachamim, based on this the sages
said: חמש עשרה נשים פוטרות צרותיהן וצרת צרותיהן מן החליצה ומן היבום
עד סוף כל העולם. chamesh esrei nashim poterot tzoroseihen v'tzarat tzoroseihen min
hachalitzah umin hayibum ad sof kol ha'olam. Fifteen women are exempt, they
exempt their wives, their co-wives, their co-co-wives, co-co-co-wives until the end. יכול
שאני מרבה אף שש עריות החמורות מאלו שיהיו צרותיהן אסורות, yachol she'ani
marbeh af sheish arayos hachamurot me'elu sheyihiyu tzoroseihen asurot, maybe I would
include even the six more weighty forbidden sexual
relationships, that their צרה tzara would be forbidden. Now, what is it
we're talking about? What six more weighty? We're dealing with pretty darn
weighty עריות arayos here. So turn the page to דף י"ג Daf
Yud Gimmel because it's referring to the next משנה. mishnah. If you
look at דף י"ג Daf Yud Gimmel for a minute,
the bottom of י"ג עמוד א', Yud Gimmel Amud Aleph, what does
it say there? Everybody got it?
It says שש עריות
חמורות מאלו.
sheish
arayos chamurot me'elu.
So we had listed fifteen, there are six that are more weighty
מפני שנשואות לאחרים mipnei shenesuot l'acherim because they are married to other
people, meaning it's more weighty in the sense that there is no
way your brother could be married to these עריות. arayos. What's an
example of somebody who's an ערווה araya to you that your brother
cannot be married to? Your mother? Your mother! Or your sister! Okay,
so in those cases, since you'll never have a case where your
brother is married to your mother or your sister, what would be
the הלכה halacha about a stranger who's married to your mother or
sister and then he dies? What would be the story about their
co-wife? מותר mutar or אסור assur to you? מותר! mutar! Because there's
no idea of יבום, yibum, right? So this is what we said
before, that it's not a הלכה halacha that an ערווה araya makes
a co-wife forbidden to you. That's only relevant in the context of
יבום. yibum. In a normal case that somebody, your sister is married
to someone and he dies, the co-wife is permissible to you because
there's no concept of יבום, yibum, right? So the whole idea of
co-wives is only since there's no יבום yibum then the co-wife becomes
אשת אח. eishes ach. Alright, so that's why it says they're more
weighty, they're more weighty in the sense that you'll never have a
scenario that your brother is married to them, and because you'll never
have that scenario, so there's never a scenario of
יבום, yibum, so the reality is co-wives are permissible. Okay, so back
to our גמרא. Gemara. So let's take a look. יכול שאני מרבה
אף שש עריות החמורות מאלו yachol she'ani marbeh af sheish arayos hachamurot
me'elu שיהיו צרותיהן אסורות, sheyihiyu tzoroseihen asurot, but maybe not. Maybe, and
this was a הוה אמינא hava amina we had yesterday also if
you remember. The idea is that an ערווה araya makes a co-wife
forbidden, forget the context of יבום. yibum. The co-wife of an ערווה
erva maybe is an ערווה. erva. Forgetting any idea of יבום, yibum,
she just forbids by context, by proximity, she forbids the co-wife. Maybe
I would say that? אמרת, amrat, no, you can respond. מה אחות
אישה מיוחדת שהיא ערווה וחייבין על זדונה כרת ועל שגגתה חטאת ואפשר
לינשא לאח. mah achot isha meyuchadet shehi ervah v'chayavin al zdonah kareis
v'al shigagatah chatas v'efshar l'hinasay l'ach. No, because the whole case we're
talking about is an ערווה araya that could be married to a
brother. In that case we say אסורה ליבם וצרתה אסורה. asurah l'yavam
v'tzarasah asurah.
She's forbidden to the brother-in-law and the co-wife is forbidden. אף כל
שהיא ערווה וחייבין על זדונה כרת ועל שגגתה חטאת ואפשר לינשא לאח,
af kol shehi ervah v'chayavin al zdonah kareis v'al shigagatah chatas v'efshar
l'hinasay l'ach, similarly by any of the other עריות arayos that could
be married to a brother. In that case אסורה ליבם, asurah l'yavam,
she's forbidden to the brother-in-law וצרתה אסורה v'tzarasah asurah and therefore her
צרה tzara is אסור. assur. יצאו שש עריות החמורות מאלו yatz'u sheish
arayos hachamurot me'elu to exclude these cases like a sister or mother,
שהרי אי אפשר לינשא לאח, sheharei ee efshar l'hinasay l'ach, since they
can't be married to a brother, צרותיהן מותרות, tzoroseihen mutarot, they don't
forbid the co-wife. The whole context of forbidding co-wives is in a
context of יבום. yibum. So therefore that's what we learned. So we
learned it all
from אחות אישה. achot isha. אחות אישה achot isha is an ערווה,
erva, could be married to a brother, there's a מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibum to discuss, she's exempt from the מצוה mitzvah and she
exempts the co-wife. And that's true by all עריות arayos that are
married to your brother that they are you're exempt from יבום yibum
and the co-wives are exempt as well. Okay, צרותיהן מותרות שאין צרה
אלא מאח. tzoroseihen mutarot she'ein tzara ela mei'ach. Okay, because the concept
of צרה tzara is only in the context of a co-wife of
your brothers, not any co-wife of any ערווה, erva, only married to
your brother. Okay. Now. Okay. אזהרה שמענו. azharah shamanu. Now the עונש.
onesh. I just want to keep on holding on to all of
these things in simple matters. So the brother brother means with the
same two parents? No, just father, just the same father. That's the
whole point with that it could be a different mother.
Exactly. Exactly. Yep. Okay. Now עשרה ששמענו Asara she-shamanu where am I?
עשרה ששמענו Asara she-shamanu now we heard that it's forbidden because it
says אשה אל אחותה לא תקח לצרור isha el achota lo tikach
litzror
don't marry a woman and her sister and the עליה aleha tells
us even in a context of יבום. yibum. So we learned from
there that there's a prohibition to do that. עונש מנין? Onesh minayin?
How do I know that if you went ahead and did the
מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum in a case of ערוה, ervah, it
would equally be punishable like any עריות? arayot? You know, maybe since
in the end of the day there's a מצוה mitzvah of יבום,
yibum, maybe it somewhat attenuates the punishment. Okay, so we've learned that
it's forbidden in the case of עריות. arayot. How do I know
that it still has the same weight of punishment? אמר קרא Amar
kra the verse says כי כל אשר יעשה מכל התועבות האלה ונכרתו.
ki kol asher ya'aseh mikol hato'evot ha'eleh venichretu.
That's at the that's the punishment by the עריות arayot after it
lists all the עריות arayot and included in that עריות arayot is
אשה אל אחותה לא תקח לצרור. isha el achota lo tikach litzror.
So once the prohibition of a wife's sister includes the case of
יבום yibum and then that is told that there's an איסור כרת,
issur kares, so we learn that the איסור כרת issur kares applies
even in the case of יבום, yibum, right? Is that clear? So
you have right אשה
אל אחותה לא תקח isha el achota lo tikach right
לא תקח לצרור lo tikach litzror right
and עליה. aleha. ולא
לגלות ערותה עליה. v'lo legallot ervatah aleha.
So this עליה aleha becomes a key word for meaning, you know,
in a case of יבום. yibum. Right? Because it says יבמה יבוא
עליה. yevamah yavo aleha. In a case of יבום. yibum. So the
prohibition of עריות arayot applies even in a case of יבום yibum
and it applies even to the צרה, tzara, that's where we get
לצרור. litzror. And then at the very end of all the עריות,
arayot, the תורה Torah says ונכרתו. venichretu.
Okay, so the חיוב כרת hiyuv kares applies even in an עריות
arayot in the context of יבום yibum because that's this is the
basis, this is the paradigm that עריות arayot in the context of
יבום yibum remains forbidden. And how do we know that it remains
forbidden? It remains חייב כרת. hayav kares.
It's the same תורה Torah of of
yeah, well that also becomes because she becomes an אשת אח, eshet
ach, so yeah.
Okay. Alright, so it says I mean once you learn that a
צרה tzara is exempt, then it again, that's what we're talking about
before, she becomes an אשת אח. eshet ach. Okay. Okay, תני Tanei
now the גמרא Gemara that's the end of the ברייתא. Braita. Now
the גמרא Gemara goes back to analyze it. תני Tanei yes.
Difference between ערוה ervah and עריות? arayot? ערוה ervah is just sort
of
like singular and describing, you know, what look, we should we should
put it on the surface because I've already been sort of acknowledging
sort of implicitly realizing this, you know, the complete male orientation of
all the discussion. Like even when I'm talking about say, so if
your wife is married and your wife's sister is married, like it's
all talking from the perspective of men, right? But similarly the idea
of the label of עריות, arayot, you know, you might we might
want to say the relationship is a forbidden relationship, it's an incestuous
relationship.
But the גמרא, Gemara, I mean it's really following the פסוקים, pesukim,
really sort of looks at the woman as forbidden. This is a
forbidden woman who is forbidden to a man. Okay? So a sister
is a forbidden a forbidden not the not the sibling is an
incestuous relationship, sister is forbidden. So therefore the word ערוה ervah really
is like is like a label to that person. The sister is
an ערוה. ervah. She's not an ערוה ervah to the whole world,
she's an ערוה ervah to the brother. But it's sort of like
sort of like a label to the, you know, of the person,
a status of the person. עריות arayot is the abstract, the prohibited
sexual relation. Okay?
כל העריות Kol ha-arayot or it's also plural, it could just mean
all the ערוות, ervas, all those people. But it's because it means
all the different ערוות, ervas, it could also become the abstract sense
of, you know, forbidden sexual relations. But ערוה ervah refers to the
person is an ערוה. ervah.
I also understood the question to also be grammatical. ערוה ervah is
singular and עריות arayot is plural.
Right, right, right.
It's the same difference between the six ערוה ervah who are not
allowed yes, that's not because of the word it's not the difference
between the words ערוה ervah and עריות. arayot. It's the same root.
Right, right, right. It's the same thing. It's just in the plural.
It's just in the plural.
Those those six are like mother's prohibited
because she'll never have a case of יבום yibum because she'll never
be married to the brother.
And the other of the fifteen are permitted on the יבום.
yibum. Right. Exactly. Well, there's a case of יבום, yibum, right? She
could be married to a brother and we could be talking of
יבום, yibum, right? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
מכדי Meichdi so, מאי mai so גמרא Gemara says
like this: טעמא דכתב רחמנא עליה, Ta'ama dekata rachmana aleha, it's because
of the עליה aleha we know that יבום yibum does not apply
in a place of in a place of מצוה mitzvah I'm sorry,
does not apply in a place of עריות, arayot, of an ערוה.
ervah. הלאו הכי halav hacha הוה אמינא, havah amina, were it not
for that פסוק, pasuk, I would have thought אחות אשה מיבמת, achot
isha meyabemet, that maybe you could even you would even do יבום
yibum in a case of an ערוה, ervah, in a case of
a wife's sister. So מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why would I have
had that הוה אמינא? havah amina? I mean it's an איסור. issur.
How could I have thought you could do it? Because presumably I
would have said אמרינן אתי עשה ודחי לא תעשה. amrinan ati asei
vedachi lo ta'asei. The positive מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum should override
the negative prohibition of sex with one with a wife's sister. So
the
גמרא Gemara says how would I have thought that? Like again, why
did I need a פסוק pasuk to tell me don't do it?
How could I have thought that? אימא דאמרינן eima de-amrinan עשה ודחי
לא תעשה, asei vidachei lo taasei, when do I say a positive
מצוה mitzvah comes and overrides a negative? לא תעשה גרידא, lo taasei
greida, when it's just a negative prohibition, it's not a weighty one
or a particular one of כרת, kares, it's a normal one. לא
תעשה שיש בו כרת, lo taasei she-yesh bo kares,
a negative prohibition that's punishable by כרת, kares, so מי דחי? mi
dachi? There's never a principle that an עשה asei overrides. Now as
I said before when I began this סוגיא, sugya, the easy answer
is yes, but the מצוה mitzvah of יבום Yibum does override one
particular מצוה mitzvah that has a כרת, kares, which is what? אשת
אח. eishes ach. So maybe if the מצוה mitzvah of יבום Yibum
overrides one עריות, arayos, אשת אח, eishes ach, maybe it would override
other עריות arayos as well? Right, that's the best הוה אמינא. hava
amina. If you're already allowing יבום Yibum to override the prohibition of
brother's sister, brother's wife, maybe it could override other prohibitions as well?
But the גמרא Gemara has not said that yet. So the גמרא
Gemara is trying to figure out why I would have had a
הוה אמינא hava amina you could do this מצוה mitzvah even in
the context of an איסור עריות. issur arayos. And to say an
עשה asei overrides a לא תעשה lo taasei is not a good
answer because this is a very weighty לא תעשה, lo taasei, it's
a לא תעשה lo taasei with כרת. kares. So why would I
have needed a פסוק? pasuk? Couldn't I have known by myself that
you're not allowed to do it?
As a risk of over-simplific- like why what about פיקוח נפש pikuach
nefesh and שבת? Shabbos? You've got an- yeah but that's not-
but we need a special פסוק pasuk to learn out that that's
allowed. That's not based on עשה דוחה לא תעשה, asei dochei lo
taasei, that's based on a special exemption. Okay. Yeah, exactly.
But no, here we're only looking for first a הוה אמינא, hava
amina, right? We want in the end to say you don't do
it, but we want to figure out what was the הוה אמינא,
hava amina, why was it even a hypothetical possibility? So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, ותו, v'tu, in addition, לא תעשה גרידא מנלן
דדחי? lo taasei greida minalan de-dachi? Now where do we even know
the ideas of an עשה asei over- and now we can, you
can sort of switch your thinking caps to a different whatever, to
a to a to a less high-grade thinking cap
because now we get into- we become into a easier conversation. We're
going to put aside יבום Yibum for a day or so and
we're going to what?
Just a day.
And we're going to talk about, in order to explore what the
הוה אמינא hava amina here was that the מצוה mitzvah of יבום
Yibum would override, we're going to explore the issue of where do
we know the idea that a positive מצוה mitzvah overrides a negative
מצוה? mitzvah? And that's going to be a general discussion, so we're
not even going to really talk about יבום Yibum for the rest
of today and it's going to be a general discussion of where
do you know a positive מצוה mitzvah overrides a negative to help
us understand why we might have thought that you could do the
מצוה mitzvah of יבום Yibum in a case of עריות. arayos.
But in this case we said we couldn't because it's a כרת
kares which is more weighty.
Right, but we want to at least begin
to
understand- but we want to understand where we got this idea.
There's one way we know this- yeah what? Anytime when someone stands
up and says oh this is an easy גמרא.
Gemara. I didn't say easy. Okay, anyway the גמרא Gemara says how
do you know that an עשה asei overrides a לא תעשה? lo
taasei? דכתיב de-ksiv because the verse says לא תלבש שעטנז, lo silbash
shatnez, do not wear שעטנז, shatnez, גדילים תעשה לך gdilim taaseh lach
and then the next verse says גדילים תעשה לך, gdilim taaseh lach,
make yourself ציצית. tzitzis. So ואמר רבי אלעזר, v'amar Rabi Elazar, סמוכין
מן התורה מנין? smuchin min hatorah minayin? How do you know that
it is legitimate to infer things from juxtapositions in the תורה, Torah,
סמוכין? smuchin? שנאמר shene'emar because the verse says סמוכים לעד לעולם עשוים
באמת וישר. smuchim la-ad le-olam asuyim be-emes ve-yashar. So from, yes, from
תהלים, Tehillim, which I, you know, which obviously means it means like
support forever and ever but here it's reading oh, סמוכין smuchin is
a good thing
to ja- juxtapose texts is a good- is something you can learn
from. So the and the derivation therefore is don't wear שעטנז, shatnez,
but if you have to wear put- you know, make שעטנז shatnez
in your ציצית. tzitzis. Now why would you have to make שעטנז
shatnez in your ציצית? tzitzis? Because of you have a linen garment
and the only כשר kosher string you can use for the blue
string is made out of wool as we will see. So if
the only possible way to make ציצית tzitzis in that context would
be to make שעטנז, shatnez, and if it's there's no other way
to make ציצית tzitzis without having it שעטנז, shatnez, you can go
ahead and have your ציצית tzitzis out of שעטנז. shatnez. So that's
where we learn from the juxtaposition. Don't wear שעטנז shatnez unless
except in the case of גדילים תעשה לך. gdilim taaseh lach. Now
of course you could have read it why don't you read it
don't wear שעטנז shatnez even in the case of גדילים תעשה לך?
gdilim taaseh lach? Alright, that's a good question. But anyway this is
our דרשה. drasha. Well, we're going to explore the whole issue so
hold on. Yes.
You could have used the בגד beged of a כהן גדול. kohen
gadol.
Uh yes, that's true, but that again could be a sort of
a specific היתר heter as opposed to this sort of represents more
as a general rule not but, you know, this more yeah it's
a good point but that would have probably been framed as an
exception.
But if you read it even, if you read it even, then
that would mean that the general הוה אמינא hava amina would be
that the עשה asei could be דוחה dochei the לא תעשה lo
taasei except in this case.
No,
שייך ביה shayach beh as in as an exception, but anyway we're
reading it as a rule and we're reading that it that that
it's except in the case. Let's let's just read a little bit
more. ואמר רב ששת אמר רבי אלעזר משום רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
מנין ליבמה,
v'amar Rav Sheshes amar Rabi Elazar
mishum Rabi Elazar ben Azaryah minayin le-yevama, so this is not exactly-
it is a יבום Yibum case, it's not exactly. It's a little
bit of a digression. How do you know that a sister-in-law שנפלה
לפני מוכה שחין, she-nafla lifnei Mukeh Shechin,
that her brother-in-law is a disgusting person, is somebody... the example the
גמרא Gemara gives of a disgusting person is somebody afflicted with like
boils?
שאין חוסמין אותו, She-ein chosmin oto, you do not muzzle her, meaning
if she's protesting and she is saying I don't want this guy
to do יבום, Yibbum, how do you know that you actually attend
to her concerns and you do not muzzle her? שנאמר, Shene'emar, לא
תחסום שור בדישו, Lo tachsom shor b'disho, do not muzzle an ox
in its threshing, וסמיך ליה, V'samich lei, and then it says right
nearby, כי ישבו אחים יחדיו, Ki yeshvu achim yachdav, the מצוה Mitzvah
of יבום. Yibbum. Okay, so that obviously is more of a policy
than of a הלכה, Halacha, but since we're talking about יבום Yibbum
and we're talking about סמוכים, smuchim, we re-introduced this דרשה drasha as
well. Okay, that you do not silence a woman who is objecting
to יבום Yibbum and finds the brother-in-law completely unacceptable. So that's a
very important idea right at the beginning because so much of this
is all like we've been saying from the man's perspective and his
מצוה Mitzvah of יבום. Yibbum. We're going to learn later that the
act of יבום Yibbum could be done even against the woman's will
and it's still binding. The woman becomes very much an object in
this whole
thing, like we're all deciding am I allowed to do יבום Yibbum
to her, not allowed to do יבום Yibbum to her, whatever, like
she completely doesn't have a voice. So it's very important here that
we're right at the beginning introducing the idea that she does have
a voice and she could actually object and we actually do attend
to that and make sure that חליצה Chalitzah gets done and not
יבום. Yibbum. So that's something that we will return to. Back to
our major topic here.
ואמר רב יוסף, V'amar Rav Yosef, אפילו למאן דלא דרש סמוכין בעלמא,
afilu l'man d'lo darash smuchim b'alma, even if in general you do
not give weight to juxtapositions, במשנה תורה דרש, b'Mishneh Torah darash, in
דברים, Devarim, משנה תורה, Mishneh Torah, where it was a repetition of
the earlier מצוות, mitzvot, there juxtapositions do matter. And that's relevant because
the juxtaposition of ציצית Tzitzit and שעטנז Shatnez is in דברים, Devarim,
which means that even people that normally would not דרש סמוכין darash
smuchim would acknowledge this דרשה drasha of ציצית Tzitzit and שעטנז Shatnez
because it's a juxtaposition in דברים Devarim and therefore would admit that
עשה דוחה לא תעשה aseh docheh lo ta'aseh because this is a
legitimate דרשה. drasha. Now let's focus on this idea, in general you
don't דרש סמוכין darash smuchim but you do by משנה תורה. Mishneh
Torah. Why would that be? Let's take a look. So דהא, de-ha,
here's the evidence, רבי יהודה בעלמא לא דרש. Rabbi Yehuda b'alma lo
darash. We know רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in general does not make
דרשות drashot based on juxtapositions. ובמשנה תורה דרש, U-v'Mishneh Torah darash, and
nevertheless he's willing to do it in משנה תורה. Mishneh Torah. So
now let's
sort of spell this out. ובעלמא מנלן דלא דרש, U-v'alma minalan d'lo
darash, where do you know that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in general
does not make דרשות drashot based on juxtapositions? דתניא, Detanya, it's taught
in a ברייתא, braita, בן עזאי אומר, Ben Azzai omer, נאמר מכשפה
לא תחיה, ne'emar machasheifa lo techayeh, it says do not suffer a
witch to live, ונאמר כל שוכב עם בהמה מות יומת, v'ne'emar kol
shochev im behemah mot yumat, and it's juxtaposed to, this is not
in דברים, Devarim, this is in שמות Shemot in משפטים, Mishpatim, anybody
who lies with an animal shall be put to death.
סמכו ענין לו, Samchu inyan lo, it juxtaposed the two. So what?
It's juxtaposing the two to tell you a הלכה. Halacha. מה שוכב
עם בהמה בסקילה, Mah shochev im behemah b'skilah, the same way sleeping
with an animal is punishable by execution and by
stoning, so אף מכשפה בסקילה, af machasheifa b'skilah, the same would be
true by a
מכשפה. machasheifa. Okay,
now, by the way, it's not telling you how you know that
sleeping with an animal is בסקילה, b'skilah, but that's learned by another
פסוק pasuk that says דמיהם בם dmeihem bam by the woman who
sleeps with an animal and חז"ל Chazal understand that דמיהם בם dmeihem
bam always means סקילה. skilah. Okay, so he learns out סקילה skilah
by a מכשפה machasheifa based on the juxtaposition. אמר ליה רבי יהודה,
Amar lei Rabbi Yehuda, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said back to
who was this? רבי שמעון? בן עזאי. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
back to בן עזאי, Ben Azzai, וכי מפני שסמכו ענין לו נוציא
זה לסקילה? V'chi mipnei she-samchu inyan lo notzi zeh l'skilah? What, just
because you've got a juxtaposition you're going to stone a guy?
So isn't that what we do all the time with דרשה? drasha?
But that doesn't mean that you can't use a דרשה drasha to
learn out something like a form of execution, but it means the
idea of juxtaposition is not a persuasive דרשה drasha for him.
Just because you've got a juxtaposition, a lot of things in the
תורה Torah are juxtaposed, right? So especially if you read like קדושים,
Kedoshim, you have פרשת קדושים, Parshat Kedoshim, the weirdest things are juxtaposed
one to another. So that's going to be a basis for a
דרשה? drasha? So you're going to stone this guy? אלא, Ela, I
agree you stone the guy, but not based on the סמיכות, smichut,
not based on a juxtaposition. אוב וידעוני בכלל מכשפים היו. Ov v'yidoni
b'chlal machasheifim hayu. So the אוב ov and ידעוני yidoni are two
types of sort of necromancy and witchcraft, so they were in the
general category. ולמה יצאו, V'lama yatz'u, why were they taken out and
they were specifically mentioned? And here the תורה Torah says, it
says באבן ירגמו אותם דמיהם בם. b'even yirgemu otam dmeihem bam. Okay,
it says explicitly by אוב וידעוני ov v'yidoni that you stone them.
So why were they taken out of the general category? for to
be explicated that they're stoned, so להקיש להם Le-hakish lahem in order
to connect to them, in order to make them an example ולומר
לך Ve-lomar lach to tell you מה אוב וידעוני בסקילה אף מכשפה
בסקילה. Ma Ov ve-Yidoni be-skila af makhshefa be-skila. The same way an
אוב וידעוני Ov ve-Yidoni gets stoned, anybody who's in that category of
witchcraft gets stoned. So basically he's not disagreeing to the הלכה. Halacha.
הלכה Halacha I agree, they get stoned, but we learn it out
from אוב וידעוני, Ov ve-Yidoni, we don't learn it out from סמוכין.
Semuchin. So you see Reb Yehuda is objects to the idea of
learning out a דרשה Drasha from סמוכין. Semuchin. That's somebody who in
general isn't doesn't דרשן Darshan סמוכין. Semuchin. Now, by the way, in
the י"ג מדות שהתורה נדרשת בהן, Yud Gimmel Middot she-ha-Torah nidreshet bahen,
סמוכין Semuchin isn't one of them, right? So דבר שהיה בכלל ויצא
מן הכלל ללמד לא ללמד על עצמו יצא אלא ללמד על הכלל
כולו יצא, Davar she-haya be-khlal ve-yatza min ha-khlal lelamed lo lelamed al
atzmo yatza ela lelamed al ha-khlal kulo yatza, that's what Reb Yehuda
just did. אוב וידעוני Ov ve-Yidoni were in the כלל Klal of
מכשפה, Makhshefa, they were taken out to tell you a הלכה Halacha
about them, they get סקילה. Sekila. It's not just about them as
an extension, it's coming to teach you about the whole כלל. Klal.
That's one of the י"ג מדות. Yud Gimmel Middot. סמוכין Semuchin is
not one of the י"ג מדות. Yud Gimmel Middot. So Reb Yehuda
in general doesn't go by סמוכין. Semuchin. So ובמשנה תורה מנלן דדרש?
U-ve-Mishneh Torah minalan de-darash? But he's prepared to do it in דברים.
Devarim. How do you know? דתנן De-tanan because we taught in the
משנה: Mishnah: נושא אדם אנוסת אביו ומפותת אביו. Noseh adam anusat aviv
u-mefutat aviv.
So one of the עריות Arayot is a is a father's wife,
even not a mother. What about if it's not a father's wife?
What about if it's a woman that the father had sex with
but not his wife, never was his wife? Okay, so again in
the גמרא Gemara that would be called אנוסת אביו Anusat aviv or
מפותת אביו, Mefutat aviv, a woman the father raped or woman the
father seduced, right? Because those are the two categories in תורה Torah
that the תורה Torah discusses of having sex in a non-marital context.
Okay, so is that included in the prohibition of father's wife or
not? So that's the question. So the משנה Mishnah says: No, actually
there's no prohibition for somebody marrying a woman that his father had
sex with. נושא אדם אנוסת אביו ומפותת אביו אנוסת בנו ומפותת בנו.
Noseh adam anusat aviv u-mefutat aviv, anusat beno u-mefutat beno. Similarly,
a man is not allowed to marry a woman who was his
daughter-in-law, but he can marry a woman that his son has had
sex with. Okay, so those are not included in the prohibition of
stepmother and daughter-in-law. All right? רבי יהודה אוסר באנוסת אביו ומפותת אביו.
Rebbe Yehuda oser be-anusat aviv u-mefutat aviv. Reb Yehuda agrees by the
case of a of a woman the son has had sex with
is not forbidden on the father, but he disagrees with the case
of a of a woman that the father has had sex with.
Okay, where does he know that from? ואמר רב גידל אמר רב
מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? Ve-amar Rav Gidal amar Rav mai ta'ama de-Rebbe
Yehuda? What's the reason of Reb Yehuda? So Reb Yehuda himself doesn't
say his reason, but we're going to give a reason and that
reason is going to be based on סמוכין. Semuchin. דכתיב, De-khitiv, the
verse says: לא יקח איש את אשת אביו ולא יגלה כנף אביו.
Lo yikach ish et eshet aviv ve-lo yigaleh knaf aviv. A man
should not marry his his father's wife, so there's the prohibition of
father's wife, and should not uncover the like the the hem of
his father, you know? So what does that mean? What what does
that add? I mean it could just be trying to say like
why it's so inappropriate, this is the woman his father you know,
but but nevertheless what halachically is that phrase adding ולא יגלה כנף
אביו? Ve-lo yigaleh knaf aviv? So he interprets it the following
way: כנף שראה אביו, Knaf she-ra'ah aviv, the same like you know
edge of the garment, you know, the sort of the the that
his father saw, so the same you know woman that his father
was with and his father was with when she was naked, so
it's sort of he sees under her skirts as it were, so
לא יגלה, Lo yigaleh, he cannot go he cannot have sex with
that woman. Okay, so he reads ולא יגלה כנף אביו Ve-lo yigaleh
knaf aviv not to be limited to father's wife but any woman
the father has had sex with. That's not a bad read of
the פסוק, Pasuk, right? Just in terms of even a פשט Pshat
that that's at least what the פסוק Pasuk is saying about the
problem of father's wife. So therefore he's generalizing that to therefore if
that's the problem of father's wife, that's a problem of any woman
the father has had sex with. Okay, now so far it's not
even סמוכין, Semuchin, it's just interpreting what the words mean. But now
we're going to bring in
סמוכין. Semuchin. וממאי דבאנוסה כתיב? U-mimai de-be-anusa ktiv? How do you really
know we're talking about a woman that the father wasn't married to?
It was a case of like a a woman who was either
raped or seduced but not married to? Because מעילויא דקרא, Me-iluya de-kraya,
because what's written earlier in the פסוק? Pasuk? דכתיב, De-khitiv, because right
before it gets to a wife a father's wife, the פסוק Pasuk
is talking about a case of rape. It says: ונתן האיש השוכב
עמה לאבי הנערה חמשים כסף, Ve-natan ha-ish ha-shochev imah la-avi ha-na'arah chamishim
kasef, right? The case of a man who rapes a woman and
he pays the father fifty units of silver and so on. So
the פרשה Parsha right before this was a פרשה Parsha of a
woman who was raped. וסמיך ליה, Ve-samikh leh, and then this פרשה
Parsha is לא יקח איש את אשת אביו. Lo yikach ish et
eshet aviv. Okay, so that's how we're proving that Reb Yehuda holds
a סמוכין. Semuchin. On the one hand Reb Yehuda, you know, rejects
סמוכין Semuchin by giving סקילה Sekila to the מכשפה Makhshefa or that's
the basis he's ready to give סקילה Sekila to the מכשפה, Makhshefa,
but he rejects that that's the basis. So in general he doesn't
hold of סמוכין. Semuchin. Here we're saying he holds of סמוכין, Semuchin,
but Reb Yehuda never said he holds this. This is us, this
is us sort of reading into what Reb Yehuda's reasoning is.
Because since the פסוק Pasuk says לא יקח איש את אשת
אביו
ולא
יגלה
כנף אביו,
Lo yikach ish et eshet aviv ve-lo yigaleh
knaf aviv, so the first thing we're saying is that Reb Yehuda
says ולא יגלה כנף אביו. Ve-lo yigaleh knaf aviv. this means any
woman, okay, that he had sex with, מפותה mefutas
or אנוסת אביו. anusat aviv. Now, even if you said that, you
could have just said that's just how he reads פשט pshat of
the פסוק. pasuk. That's not סמוכין. smuchin. But right before here it
says, you know, the problem is that here it's also talking about
a father, but it's talking about ונתן האיש השכב, venatan ha-ish hashochev,
right, עם האשה, im ha-isha, עם ה... im ha-... no, what's the
פסוק? pasuk? לאבי הנערה. l-avi ha-na'ara. ולא יקח איש את אשת אביו.
lo yikach ish et eshet aviv. ולא יגלה. velo yigaleh. ונתן האיש
השכב עמה
לאבי הנערה.
venatan ha-ish
hashochev imah
l-avi ha-na'ara. לאבי הנערה.
l-avi ha-na'ara. לאבי הנערה. l-avi ha-na'ara. ונתן האיש השכב עמה לאבי הנערה.
venatan ha-ish hashochev imah l-avi ha-na'ara. חמשים כסף. chamishim kasef. לאבי הנערה
חמשים כסף. l-avi ha-na'ara chamishim kasef.
So
now don't let לאבי הנערה l-avi ha-na'ara distract you. The point is
this is a case of אנוסה, anusa, of a woman who was
raped. And since that's right before it, that reinforces the idea that
this extra phrase ולא יגלה כנף אביו velo yigaleh knaf aviv is
a woman that the father raped or a woman that the father
had sex with in a non-marital context, because that was the discussion
above was a sex in a non-marital context.
Otherwise it's an opaque phrase, we
don't know what it means. Right, okay, so there you see רב
יהודה Reb Yehuda is דורש סמוכין doresh smuchin in משנה תורה. Mishneh
Torah. Okay, now let's read a little bit more.
Maybe even say that that teaches you that you can be דורש
סמוכין.
doresh smuchin. Oh, that's interesting. Since it's opaque and the only way
you understand context is through, maybe that's a nice point. Okay, one
minute. ורבנן, V-rabbanan, now what would the Rabbis say back? Before we
get back to our major theme. They would say, אי הוי סמיך
ליה כדקאמרת. ee hava samich lei k-de-ka-amrat. If it was immediately juxtaposed,
if this came right after, you'd be right. But the problem is
you have this line interrupts them. השתא דלא סמיך ליה. hashata d-lo
samich lei. Here it's not directly juxtaposed. And the parenthesis is probably
a later gloss to spell out what that means. דכתיב לא יקח
איש את אשת אביו בינתיים. de-chtiv lo yikach ish et eshet aviv
beinteyim. Okay, clearly you see it's a gloss because it's not written
in Aramaic, the tone shifts. Anyway, but here that it's not directly
juxtaposed, it doesn't come to include a woman the father had sex
with. So what does that phrase mean? בשומרת יבם הכתוב מדבר. beshomeret
yavam hakatuv medaber. Now, a שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam.
Now, this is, what does that mean? They say it does not
mean a woman the father had sex with. This means a woman
who is similar to the father's wife. Now, what woman is similar
to a father's wife? Well, if you ask me, what's a similar
case, it would be a woman he had sex with. But no,
they're rejecting that. So what's a woman that's quasi-married to the father?
Any thoughts? פילגש. pilegesh. Well, פילגש, pilegesh, but in our context, it's
a woman who the father has a מצווה mitzvah of יבום yibum
with. Okay? The father's brother, okay, here's a father is ראובן, Reuven,
we're back to יבום, yibum, שמעון Shimon here died and left over
a wife, right, I don't know, רחל. Rachel. So רחל Rachel here
is ולא יגלה כנף אביו. lo yigaleh knaf aviv. רחל Rachel is
a woman that is a quasi-wife to the father. Okay? Because there's
a מצווה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, there's זיקה, zikah, right, we've already
introduced this idea that a יבום yibum is like a quasi-marriage that
has to then be fully actualized through the act of יבום. yibum.
Potential. Okay, so what they say is this is not just some
woman he had sex with. It has to still be more in
the context of אשת אביו. eshet aviv. What's in the context of
אשת אביו? eshet aviv? A woman that the father should be marrying,
is quasi-married, a woman that he has a מצווה mitzvah of יבום
yibum with. Okay? Now, ולאוו עליה בשני לאווין. v-lavu aleih b-shnei lavin.
But the point is you really don't need a פסוק pasuk to
tell you that to tell this guy, who is this guy, let's
say this is שמעון, Shimon, this is ראובן, Reuven, what's one of
ראובן's Reuven sons? Anybody remember?
בכורי. Bachorei. Okay, whoever. Anyway, what, here we'll call him ראובן Reuven
Junior. Okay. So ראובן Reuven Junior here, okay, there's already a reason
he cannot have sex with רחל, Rachel, even if שמעון Shimon died.
You know why? Why can't he? It's not just because it's his
father, the woman his father has a מצווה mitzvah of יבום yibum
to. You know why he can't? Because
it's
his aunt.
His aunt!
Aunt! Okay? Right? So you really don't need a פסוק pasuk to
say that he can't have sex with the woman his father has
a מצווה mitzvah of יבום yibum to because that woman is his
aunt. Okay? So anyway, so that's why it says ולאוו עליה בשני
לאווין. v-lavu aleih b-shnei lavin. So really it's telling you that special
case and that's just to give you another prohibition, really, but it's
not coming to tell you a woman that the father had sex
with.
Now just more clarification,
is an אנוסה anusah or
a מפותה mefutah not the person's wife simply because he didn't have
intent for it to be so when he had sex with her?
Right, otherwise had he had the כוונה... kavanah...
yeah, but then you need עדים edim and whatever, yes, but so
there... yes, that's true, but that's correct. But it's not just intent.
Okay, now, so now we've established that you can not דורש סמוכין
darshan smuchin in general and דורש darshan it in משנה תורה. Mishneh
Torah. And therefore all of this is to lead up to the
idea that everybody should agree to the דרשה drasha by ציצית tzitzit
and everybody should agree to the principle that an עשה asei overrides
a לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. Now, before we get back to that,
let's understand why in משנה תורה Mishneh Torah *Mishneh Torah* you're more
entitled to דרשן *darshen* סמוכין *smuchin* than in the rest of the
תורה Torah *Torah*. If anything, the logic would have been the opposite.
The rest of the תורה Torah *Torah* is straight from God, משנה
תורה Mishneh Torah *Mishneh Torah* is משה רבינו *Moshe Rabbeinu*’s recapping of
it. So if you want to give the word that sometimes is
used about חז"ל *Chazal* look at the פסוקים psukim *psukim* is the
omni-significance, every single tittle and jot and everything is teaching you something,
you would be more inclined to do that in the first four
books than in the last one, which is the משה *Moshe* recapping.
So what's this idea that you can דרשן *darshen* סמוכין *smuchin* in
משנה תורה Torah *Mishneh Torah*? So let's take a look. So ובמשנה
תורה Torah מאי טעמא דדרש *U’vemishneh Torah mai taama d’darish*—why are you
allowed to be דרש סמוכין *daresh smuchin*? Everybody would agree in משנה
תורה *Mishneh Torah*. אי בעית אימא ee ba'it eima, משום דמוכח *Iba’is
eima mishum d’muchach*—either because it's evident in that context, it's clearly that
that's what the תורה *Torah*’s trying to communicate. We're going to explain
what that means. ואי בעית אימא *V’iba’is eima*—if you want I could
say משום דמופני *mishum d’mufni*—because it's considered superfluous. Now let's spell this
out. אי בעית אימא משום דמוכח *Iba’is eima mishum d’muchach*—it's evident, דאם
כן לכתוב רחמנא גבי עריות *de’im ken
lichtov Rachmana gabei arayos*. Meaning, here's the point. It says
that when the things are repeated in משנה תורה *Mishneh Torah*, then
the question
is there's a sense of why are they repeated here and they
wasn't in their original context? So why would you be saying לא
lo יגלה כנף אביו *lo yigaleh knaf aviv* here?
If the idea was to tell you—if it wasn't for the purpose
of juxtaposing and learning something else, if it was to tell you
the case of שומרת יבם *shomeres yavam*, if it was to tell
you that there's some other type of עריות *arayos* that's generally
true, then why wasn't it written back where the תורה *Torah* lists
the עריות *arayos* in אחרי מות קדושים *Acharei Mos Kedoshim*? Why was
it listed here? Why is it new here and it wasn't already
present in the first time in its original context? So if it's
a new thing that's being introduced here and it didn't come up
in its original context, it must be it's being introduced in order
to tell you something that's unique to this context that can be
inferred from this particular context in which it's appearing, which is an
interesting idea in general if you think about the idea that דברים
Devarim *Devarim* again is a recap. So when you recap things, when
you retell them, you wind up sometimes framing them differently, putting them
in a different context, telling them in a different sequence, nuancing things
differently. And what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is interestingly doing is it's
sort of saying let's use that as the basis of a דרשה
drasha *drasha*. Like when משה רבינו *Moshe Rabbeinu* is recapping this, well
why's he saying this if it wasn't said earlier and it's being
said in a different context here? And maybe the very fact that
it's being said now and not earlier and in a different context
is coming to tell us something very specific that we should learn
out from the context in which it's appearing. So that's the idea
of מוכח *muchach*. But again that's why there's normally an argument to
be made about מוכח *muchach* in משנה תורה *Mishneh Torah* if something
was not in its original context and is newly being introduced here.
ואי בעית אימא *V’iba’is eima*—if you want I could say משום דמופני
*mishum d’mufni*—it's extra. What do you mean it's extra? דאם כן לכתוב
רחמנא לא יקח איש את אשת אביו ולא יגלה כנף *De’im ken
lichtov Rachmana lo yikach ish es eshes aviv velo yigaleh knaf*, period.
אביו למה לי lama li? *Aviv lama li*? Why did it need—the
question of how to read this line, תוספות *Tosafos* has two versions,
I'm just reading it this way. Why did it have to say
the extra word אביו *aviv*? It could have just said ולא יגלה
כנף *velo yigaleh knaf*. Of course we're talking about the father. So
the extra word אביו *aviv* is coming to tell you that there's
something extra to דרשן *darshen* here. Now that's less interesting because that's
not something unique about משנה תורה *Mishneh Torah*, that's just saying sometimes
we have an extra word so we'll דרשן *darshen* it. So saying
that it's because this word is extra or the phrase is extra
allows me to דרשן סמוכין *darshen smuchin* is not something that's interesting
about משנה תורה *Mishneh Torah*, but the idea that we look at
this and we compare it to how it appeared earlier in the
תורה *Torah* and we note the differences and therefore we're going to
infer something from the way it's phrased, that is something that's distinctive
to משנה תורה *Mishneh Torah*. But anyway moving on, שמע מינה לאפנויי
shema mina l'afnuyei. *shma mina l’afnu-ei*—it must be that it's made extra.
So you see that we should be willing to do a דרשה
*drasha* by משנה תורה *Mishneh Torah* in דברים Devarim *Devarim* by סמוכין
*smuchin* and therefore everybody should learn out by ציצית Tzitzit? *tzitzis* there's
a principle of עשה דוחה לא תעשה asei docheh lo ta'asei. *aseh
docheh lo taaseh*. Now we're going to say that. And by ציצית
Tzitzit. *tzitzis* as well, וגבי ציצית Tzitzit נמי *vegabei tzitzis nami*, at
ציצית Tzitzit *tzitzis* as well everybody should agree to this דרשה *drasha*
by learning out that ציצית tzitzis *tzitzis* can be in a case
of שעטנז shatnez *shaatnez*. אי בעית אימא משום דמוכח *Iba’is eima mishum
d’muchach*—either because it's evident in context that the juxtaposition is communicating something.
ואי בעית אימא *V’iba’is eima*—if you want, משום דמופני *mishum d’mufni*—because it's
superfluous. Let's spell that out. אי בעית אימא משום דמוכח *Iba’is eima
mishum d’muchach*—it's evident in context. דאם כן לכתוב רחמנא גבי פרשת ציצית
tzitzis. *De’im ken lichtov Rachmana gabei parashas tzitzis*. Again, this is really
the strong argument about what makes why משנה תורה *Mishneh Torah* there's
a unique lens we bring to our דרשות *drashos* in משנה תורה
*Mishneh Torah*. Why is this thing like גדילים תעשה לך *gedilim taaseh
lach*—what's the פסוק *pasuk*? No, not גדילים תעשה לך *gedilim taaseh lach*.
It's לא תלבש lo tilbash שעטנז shatnez. גדילים תעשה לך *lo silbash
shaatnez gedilim taaseh lach*. Why is it גדילים תעשה לך *gedilim taaseh
lach* here in דברים, Devarim. right? Why not, why wasn't it written
back in במדבר, Bemidbar, back in שלח Shlach with ציצית? Why is
it being repeated here? It's not, is it adding anything? We already
know you do ציצית. So, if it's being repeated here, it must
be being repeated to tell us something unique about the context that
we can learn out from the context in which it's being repeated.
Okay, so that's a general hermeneutics, that if דברים Devarim repeats things
that are earlier and it's repeating them tends to be repeating them
in a different context and earlier they appeared in a more natural
context, so we should be able to be learning something from the
new context in which they appear and there's something that is being
communicated by the new context in which they are appearing.
First thing I notice although looking here is it does not say
ציצית תעשה לך, Tzitzit ta'aseh lach, it says...
all right, fine. And we'll get to something like that in a
minute. Okay, אי בעית אימא, one minute. מאי הלכתא דכתביה הכא, mai
hilcheta dechtaviah hacha,
why was it written here? To tell me something about the new
context. אי בעית אימא משום דהוי מופנה, ee ba'it eima mishum dehavy
mufneh, or I could learn out because it's extra. What's extra? מכדי
כתיב ובגד כלאים שעטנז לא יעלה עליך. michdee ketiv u'veged kilayim shatnez
lo ya'aleh alecha.
So now not ציצית is extra, but the איסור issur of שעטנז
shatnez. is extra. It says already in ויקרא, Vayikra, don't wear שעטנז.
shatnez Okay, לא תלבש שעטנז למה לי? lo tilbash shatnez lama li?
Why does it repeat it here? שמע מינה לאפנויי. shma mina l'afnuyei
So if it's being repeated and it's superfluous, so either in משנה
תורה things maybe something things are either in משנה תורה repeated or
in a different context. So if they're, you know, in either way
we could say let's learn something from the fact, why bother repeating?
Must be to teach me something new. Why bother putting it in
a new context? Must be to teach me something new. So since
it's repeated here, therefore I'm able to learn something from the juxtaposition
and what I learn from the juxtaposition is that the מצוה mitzvah
of ציצית overrides the prohibition of שעטנז. shatnez, Charlie, you've been trying
to say something.
Oh,
why couldn't you make the same principle not just with דברים Devarim.
but also with במדבר? Bemidbar? There's מצוות mitzvot in...
right, so that's true, you could, but I think as a general
rule,
what the גמרא Gemara is doing is pointing out two general things
which are true about דברים. Devarim, Number one is there's a lot
of מצוות mitzvot which are repeated and all of them then you
could say why repeat it, right? And so if it's being repeated,
it's being repeated to teach you something new. And there's a lot
of מצוות mitzvot that appear in a different context and in a
less natural context than they appeared earlier. So then we could say,
well, what are you trying to teach me by putting it into
this new context? In principle, you could use those two arguments elsewhere,
but there's a pre, like there's like there's a well-trodden, you know,
sort of path to go that way in דברים Devarim because that's
very natural to the whole book of דברים. Devarim Yes.
Does the גמרא Gemara have something to say about every מצוה mitzvah
which is repeated?
Right, so probably not. Probably we do it when we're interested in
doing it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
so now the גמרא's Gemara going to challenge the idea that שעטנז
shatnez is superfluous, its repetition is superfluous, and it's only there to
teach me the principle of עשה דוחה לא תעשה. asei doche lo
sa'asei, So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, הני מצטריכי, hani mitztrechi,
you need both פסוקים psukim about שעטנז, shatnez, the one in ויקרא
Vayikra and the one in דברים, Devarim because דכתב רחמנא dichatav rachmana
לא יעלה עליך. lo ya'aleh alecha. Okay,
I'm going to write down these פסוקים psukim. because they're going to
be relevant
because of the slightly different language used. So in ויקרא Vayikra you
have ובגד כלאים
שעטנז לא יעלה עליך
u'veged kilayim shatnez lo ya'aleh
alecha
and in דברים you have
לא תלבש שעטנז צמר ופשתים יחדיו.
lo tilbash shatnez tzemer u'pishtim
yachdav. So the first thing to note is this tells me what
שעטנז shatnez is made out of and the verbs are different. This
is יעלה, ya'aleh, put on you, and this is wear. Okay, so
let's see why the גמרא Gemara says that you actually need both
פסוקים. psukim. הני מצטריכי, hani mitztrechi, you need both. דאי כתב רחמנא
de'ee katav rachmana לא יעלה עליך, lo ya'aleh alecha, if it just
said don't put on you, הוה אמינא כל דרך העלאה אסרה רחמנא,
hava amina kol derech ha'ala'ah asrah rachmana, any type of putting on
you the תורה forbade, even if it's not in the form of
wearing. ואפילו מוכרי כסות, va'afilu mochrei chsus, the גמרא Gemara deals with
a case of people that sell garments and the way they carry
their garments is by putting like twenty coats one on top of
the other or twenty shirts, so it's on them but it's not
in a form of wearing.
So כתב רחמנא לא תלבש שעטנז, katav rachmana lo tilbash shatnez, therefore
it has to use the verb of wear, don't wear שעטנז, shatnez.
דומיא דלבישה, dumya d'levisha, something similar to wearing, דאית בה הנאה, de'it
beh hana'ah, that there's some type of, you know, of a benefit,
of a warmth benefit or of a covering of yourself benefit, not
something that is just a form of transporting. Now I should say
by the way that לא תלבש lo silbash... is not limited to
just cases of wearing. You could have a case of wearing that's
not considered לבישה, levisha, like wearing ten garments one on top of
the other where it's not for
the... Since it does the same function of wearing, it provides warmth,
it is forbidden. Okay? So it's really the combination of the two.
It has to be like—what—it has to be something that's like classic
wearing, which is something that provides warmth, etc. So if you wear
ten garments for transporting them, you don't transgress. But it's not limited
to just wearing, it includes cases of putting on you, when putting
on you is similar to wearing. Okay?
Like covering yourself with a blanket.
That's a ציצית question, not a שעטנז shatnez, question.
So the עיקר דכתב רחמנא
ikar
de-chasav rachmana לא תלבש...
lo silbash let me mention these two in the same...
right—and—and if the תורה just said don't wear, הוי אמינא דוקא לבישה—only
hava amina davka levisha literally wearing דאית ביה הנאה, de-is bei hana'ah,
because there's a lot of benefit, pleasure, you get from wearing something.
אבל העלאה, aval ha'ala'ah, like a blanket, לא—maybe a blanket would not
have a prohibition of שעטנז. shatnez So כתב רחמנא לא יעלה עליך.
kasav rachmana lo ya'aleh alecha. So therefore it says לא יעלה. lo
ya'aleh. So you need both פסוקים. You need לא תלבש lo silbash
to tell me that—that it has to be a type of a
benefit that's similar to לבישה, levisha, and you can wear—and it's not
just putting it on you. But you need העלאה ha'ala'ah to tell
me it's not just wearing, even something like a blanket. So anyway,
how do you say that the verse is superfluous? So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, no, אם כן לכתוב רחמנא לא תלבש שעטנז.
im kein lichtov rachmana lo silbash shatnez. צמר
ופשתים למה לי. tzemer u-fishtim lama li. I'm going to tell you
what's superfluous. What's superfluous is not this. We need the verb לא
תלבש lo silbash, to help modify the verb יעלה. ya'aleh. What's superfluous
is צמר ופשתים יחדו. tzemer u-fishtim yachdav. Now if you would ask
me, that is the least superfluous thing here, because what the heck
is שעטנז, shatnez right? This is finally telling you what שעטנז shatnez
is. But the גמרא's Gemara going to tell me why that's superfluous.
Okay, let's take a look. למה לי? מכדי, michdi, let's take a
look. כתוב ובגד כלאים שעטנז לא יעלה עליך. kasuv u-veged kilayim shatnez
lo ya'aleh alecha.
And I'm going to tell you that I could have figured out
myself that that meant—that it meant wool and linen. דתנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל, de-tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, we teach in the house of Rabbi
Yishmael, כל בי נמרו בתורה סתם בגדים—the kol bi nimru ba-Torah stam
begadim Torah generally talks about garments. ופרט לך הכתוב באחד מהם צמר
ופשתים—and u-ferat lecha ha-kasuv be-echad mei-hem tzemer u-fishtim in one place it
specifically mentions garments of wool and garments of linen. That's in the
case where it deals with צרעת. tzara'as. It talks about בבגד צמר
או בבגד פשתים. be-veged tzemer o be-veged pishtim. So there's one place
where the תורה wanted identifying בגדים—talks begadim about two primary types of
בגדים, begadim, wool and linen. So אף—so af therefore, באחד מהם צמר
ופשתים אף כל צמר ופשתים. be-echad mei-hem tzemer u-fishtim af kol tzemer
u-fishtim.
So every time it says בגד, beged, it means צמר ופשתים. tzemer
u-fishtim. So since it says בגד, beged, and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
says בגד beged always means either צמר, tzemer, a wool garment, or
a linen garment, and if this is talking about mixing garments, so
the only way you can mix garments is you mix the wool
with the linen. So I already would have known it. So why
do you have to say צמר ופשתים יחדו? tzemer u-fishtim yachdav? So
צמר ופשתים דכתב רחמנא למה לי? tzemer u-fishtim de-chasav rachmana lama li?
Why does it have to say that in בגדים? begadim? שמע מינה
לאפנויי—to make it superfluous and to show me, to use it for
the דרשה of עשה דוחה לא תעשה, to put it in juxtaposition
with the מצוה mitzvah of ציצית. גמרא Gemara says, one minute, one
minute. ואכתי אצטריך, ve-achti itzterich, I still need it to tell me
that. Why? סלקא דעתך אמינא העלאה היא דלא נפיש הנאה, salka dachasach
amina ha'ala'ah hi de-lo nafish hana'ah,
because the גמרא's Gemara going to say like this, here where it
says לא יעלה, lo ya'aleh, not לא תלבש, lo silbash so העלאה
ha'ala'ah is a lesser pleasure and a benefit than wearing something. So
maybe here I would have used רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and I
would have said when it's just a blanket, you only transgress if
it's wool and linen. אבל לבישה, aval levisha, but wearing, דנפיש הנאה,
de-nafish hana'ah, the verse in דברים where it's wearing and there's a
lot of pleasure, so maybe כל תרי מיני אסר רחמנא, kol terei
minei asar rachmana, maybe any
mixed—any types of—of fabrics that are mixed together. So here, because it's
a more serious act, maybe the definition of שעטנז shatnez, would have
been a broader definition. So that's why it had to repeat the
idea that it's wool and linen, to tell me that it's the
same definition of שעטנז shatnez. even though it's a more serious act.
Okay, so let's just read that. I would have said, סלקא דעתך
אמינא העלאה היא דלא נפיש הנאה, salka dachasach amina ha'ala'ah hi de-lo
nafish hana'ah,
the verse in ויקרא Vayikra is about putting it on you, there's
not a lot of benefit of pleasure, and therefore it's only a
very limited definition of שעטנז, shatnez of what we learned from רבי
ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, בגד beged meaning wool and linen. אבל לבישה, aval
levisha, but wearing, דנפיש הנאה, de-nafish hana'ah, the verse in דברים where
it's wearing and there's a lot of pleasure, so maybe כל תרי
מיני אסר רחמנא, kol terei minei asar rachmana, maybe any two fabrics,
different fabrics would have been—it would have been a broader definition of
שעטנז. So the תורה has to say צמר ופשתים. tzemer u-fishtim. So
it has to say צמר ופשתים tzemer u-fishtim to explicitly tell me
that it's limited to wool and linen. Okay, so the גמרא says,
so we're back to the point. You needed everything. You needed לא
תלבש to introduce the new verb. You needed צמר ופשתים tzemer u-fishtim
to re-emphasize that even if we could have figured it out here,
to re-emphasize that in both cases the definition of שעטנז is wool
and linen. So there's nothing extra. So the גמרא *Gemara* is still
going to say something is extra. Let's just, and we'll end with
that, the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: אם כן לשתוק קרא מיניה
ותישי *Im ken, lishtok kera minei, veteishei* שעטנז שעטנז *Shatnez Shatnez*. No,
no, no, I still didn't need צמר ופשתים *Tzemer Upishtin*, I could
have learned it out from a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* of שעטנז
שעטנז *Shatnez Shatnez* מהלא *meh-hala*. Okay. So therefore, since it says שעטנז
*Shatnez* here and it says שעטנז *Shatnez* here, I could have used
that to teach me that it's wool and linen. So we're back
to the idea that this פסוק *pasuk* already gave me from the
word בגד *beged* the idea of wool and linen, this פסוק *pasuk*
I needed לא תלבש *lo tilbash* to introduce the verb, but the
idea of wool and linen I would have got from just the
word שעטנז *Shatnez*. So therefore, this phrase is seen as superfluous and
that lets me make the דרשה *drasha*. So what have we said
until now? We're still half, only halfway into the argument. What we've
said is, we're trying to prove why you needed a פסוק *pasuk*,
why I would have thought יבום *yibum* overrides the עריות *arayos*. And
at least the foundation of that is a concept that an עשה
*asei* overrides a לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh*. And now we're exploring the
idea of עשה *asei* overrides לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh*. We're getting that
from the juxtaposition of כלאים *kilayim* and ציצית *tzitzis* in דברים *Devarim*,
and we're trying to argue that everybody agrees to this principle. Even
people that don't normally דרשן *darshan* סמוכים *semuchim*, דרשן *darshan* it in
דברים *Devarim*. Why? Why do we have more of a license to
do it in דברים *Devarim*? Either because it's a new context, so
that's clearly this is a new context, putting it right up against,
or ציצית *tzitzis* is a new context, ציצית *tzitzis*'s more natural context
is back in פרשת שלח *Parshas Shelach*. So that the new context
allows us to דרשן *darshan* it, or because there's something superfluous. And
what we've identified as superfluous is צמר ופשתים יחדו *tzemer upishtim yachdav*.
But what the basic thrust of all of this is to tell
us that everybody agrees to this דרשה *drasha* of כלאים בציצית *kilayim
be-tzitzis*, עשה דוחה לא תעשה *asei dochei lo ta'aseh*, learned out from
the juxtaposition, and that's going to be the foundation of why I
might have thought that the מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום *yibum* can apply
even in a case of עריות *arayos*. Okay, so clear at this
point at least, roughly? All right. Like I said, this wasn't an
easy דף *daf* right here.
All right, so to be continued tomorrow.